<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Godly and short treatise vpon the Lordes prayer, the xii articles of the Christian faith, and the Ten commaundementes.</title>
            <author>Some, Robert, 1542-1609.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1580</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06348</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16814.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2219</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23156289</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23156289</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26314</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06348)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26314)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1799:17, 2355:6b)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Godly and short treatise vpon the Lordes prayer, the xii articles of the Christian faith, and the Ten commaundementes.</title>
                  <author>Some, Robert, 1542-1609.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed in London at the three Cranes in the Vintree, by Thomas Dawson, for George Bishop.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1580..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Robert Some by STC (2nd ed.) at 22906.5.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁸ C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border, initial, tailpieces.</note>
                  <note>Bound following STC 22906 at reel 2355:6b.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: copy at 2355:6b lacks all before B1.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in: Lambeth Palace Library (reel 1799:17) and British Library (reel 2355:6b).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ten commandments --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26314:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26314:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ A Godly and ſhort Treatiſe vpon the Lordes Prayer, the xii. Articles of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith, and the ten Commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed in London</hi> at the three Cranes in the Vintree, by Thomas Daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for George Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, 1580.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:26314:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26314:2"/>
            <head>¶ Prayer is a lifting vp of <hi>the heart vnto GOD.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The Lordes Prayer.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Lordes prayer hath ſixe petitions. The three firſt concerne GOD: The three laſt, vs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr Father which art in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Two things muſt bee conſidered of vs, when we bende our ſelues to praier: Firſt, Gods loue conteyned in theſe woordes, <hi>Our Father:</hi> Secondly, Gods power contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in theſe words, <hi>Which art in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> God is our father, becauſe we are his chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren. Yf this be true, howe is Chriſte the onely ſonne of GOD? both are true: Chriſt is Gods ſonne by nature: <hi>Ioh. cap. 1. ver. 14.</hi> we by adoption. <hi>Rom. chap. 8. ver. 15. Galat. cap. 4. ver. 6.</hi> That which was his by nature, is ours by grace. We
<pb facs="tcp:26314:3"/>pray vnto God in the name of Chriſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, for God is our father by the meanes of Chriſt. If it be ſo, then Chriſt is the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone Mediatour of inteceſſion. <hi>1. Tim. chap. 2. ver. 5. Rom. cap 8. ver. 34. Heb. chap. 7. ver. 25.</hi> So are Angelles and dead Sainctes barred from this office. The ſacrifice of Chriſts death and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall interceſſion are neceſſarily linked together, they are two parts of Chriſtes Prieſthood. <hi>Heb. 5. &amp; 7. Chapters.</hi> If we graunt Angels or dead Saincts to be <hi>Interceſſours,</hi> we giue vnto them the glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Chriſtes</hi> Prieſthood.</p>
               <p>Wee haue all one father, therefore <hi>vnitie</hi> is required among vs. <hi>Math. cap. 5. ver. 23.24. Epheſi. chap 4. ver. 3.4.5.6.</hi> Vnitie I meane, in Chriſte. <hi>Rom. chap. 15. ver. 5. Philip. chap. 4 ver. 2.</hi> For without Chriſte it is accurſed. Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is godly diſcord then wicked concord. GOD is our Father, wee ought not therefore too diſpayre of his mercy. Our ſinnes I confeſſe, doe throwe vs downe to Hell. <hi>Eſay. chap. 59. ver. 2. Rom. chap. 6. ver. 23.</hi> Though they be gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous
<pb facs="tcp:26314:3"/>and many, yet Gods mercy is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all. <hi>Eſay chap. 1. ver. 18. Ezech. cap 18. ver. 23.</hi> The earthly father cannot but be good to his vngracious childe, if he returne from his lewdneſſe. <hi>Luke. chap. 15. ver. 20.21.22.23.24.</hi> Gods mercy is more exceeding. <hi>Eſay. cap. 49. ve. 14.16. 1. Timoth. chap. 1. ver. 13.14.15.16.</hi> If it be compared with the other, it is as a great Sea vnto a litle Riuer. Gods po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is ſet foorth in theſe wordes, <hi>Which art in heauen,</hi> whereby is ment that all thinges whatſoeuer are vnder the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the eternall God, and that al thinges are ordered by his Prouidence. <hi>Pſalme 115. ver. 3.</hi> Though God be in heauen hee is not there ſhut vp. Such thoughtes muſt bee farre from vs: for the Heauen of Heauens cannot conteyne him. <hi>2. Chronicles, chapt. 2. ver. 6.</hi> GOD by this ſpeache is exempted from beeyng a Creature, and wee are taught not too thinke baſely of ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie a GOD, for hee is higher then all the worlde.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26314:4"/>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1 Hallowed be thy name.</hi> Wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that Gods name may be famous and reuerenced in all the earth, yf it is to bee reuerenced, then muſt we neuer ſpeake or thinke of God without great reuerence: it is too bee wiſhed that all were thus affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted: but if none were, God abideth faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, he cannot deny him ſelfe. <hi>2. Timoth, cap. 2. ver. 13.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2 Thy kingdome come.</hi> Wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that the luſtes of our fleſhe, wicked thoughtes, and ſuch like may be ſubdued, &amp; that Gods ſpirit may rule in our harts. This is brought to paſſe, partly by the worde preached, partly by the holy ſpirit: who if hee touche not our heartes, as the woorde doeth pearce our eares, the worde is a <hi>ſhut booke. Eſay. chap. 29. ver. 11.</hi> and as a ſealed letter vnto vs. We doe well in praying dayly, <hi>Thy kingdome come,</hi> for it is encreaſed by continuall goinges forwarde euen in the beſt men. <hi>Philip. chap. 3. ver. 12. Coloſſi. chap. 1. ver. 9.10.</hi> Wee are all in a race and ſhort of the macke, whileſt wee are in the fleſhe, wee muſt goe from faith too faith,
<pb facs="tcp:26314:4"/>and from vertue to vertue, <hi>Prouerb. cap. 4. ver. 18. Epheſians chap. 4. ver. 15.</hi> There muſt be no ſtanding <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>il: not to go forwarde in a godly life is to goe backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3 Thy will be doone in earth, as it is in heauen.</hi> The wyll of God is of two ſortes. The fyrſt ſecrete: the ſeconde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed in his woorde. None can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande Gods ſecrete will. <hi>Eſay. chap. 46. ver. 10. Rom. cap. 9. ver. 19.</hi> his reuealed wyl is meant in this place: ſo that this is the meaning: we deſire that all creatures may bee obedient to Gods will reuealed in his woorde without muttering or reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce. The Angels doe execute his wil. <hi>Pſalm. 103. ver. 20.</hi> We muſt doe the like ſo neare as we can.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4 Geue vs this day our dayly bread.</hi> By Bread are vnderſtanded al things ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſary for this life, as meate, drinke, and ſuch like. <hi>2. Kinges chap. 6. ver. 22.23.</hi> It is called our bread, not becauſe of right it is due vntoo vs, but becauſe by Gods good will it is appoynted for our
<pb facs="tcp:26314:5"/>vſe. <hi>Pſalme 145. ver. 15.16.</hi> If wee will bee fed of the Lorde, wee muſt abſtayne from other mens goods, and bee content with our owne, <hi>Prouerb. chap. 5. ver. 15. Gen. chap. 3. ver. 19.2. Theſſ. cap. 3. ver. 12.</hi> The worde <hi>dayly</hi> ſignifieth ſuche prouiſion as may godly bee come by, though it bee neuer ſo homely, it taketh away all deſire of delicates. I neither doe nor dare condemne great fare, dayntie prouiſion, and ſuche like. Gods giftes doe ſerue not onely for neceſſitie, but alſo for pleaſure, <hi>Pſalm 104. ver. 15.</hi> we may vſe them I ſay for pleaſure, wee may not abuſe them: They which thynke other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe, do thinke amiſſe. Theſe wordes <hi>this day,</hi> doe take away diſtruſtfull care for the time to come, which is condemned by Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Math. chap. 6. ver. 25.28.31.34.</hi> Riche men haue Sellers full of Oyle. Garners full of Wheate, what need they to aſke? they haue enough alreadie. I graunt they haue great ſtore: but all is nothing without Gods bleſſing. Yf the ſtaffe of bread be broken: <hi>Leuit.
<pb facs="tcp:26314:5"/>chap. 26. ver. 26. Ezech. chap. 9 ver. 16.</hi> If God blowe vppon our corne: <hi>Aggeus chap. 1. ver. 9.</hi> It wil do vs no good. Man liueth not by breade onely, but by euery worde that proceedeth out of the mouth of God. <hi>Deut chap. 8. ver. 3.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee pray for bread: notwithſtanding our praiers, it is Gods gift. <hi>Pſa. 145. ver. 15.16.</hi> If the leaſt things be Gods gifts, then eternall life much more. <hi>Rom. chap 6. ver. 23.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And forgiue vs our treſpaſſes.</hi> By <hi>Treſpaſſes</hi> are ment ſinnes. Sinne is threache of Gods Lawe. <hi>1. Iohn chap. 3 ver. 4.</hi> Eyther in word, deede, or thought. None are free from ſinne. <hi>Prouerb. cap. 24. ver. 16. Luke chap. 1. ver. 47. 1. Iohn. cap. ver. 8.10.</hi> Al haue neede of pardon: for al deſire forgeuenes of theyr ſinnes. If Gods children haue need to be pardoned, they are none of gods which ſay they need not forgiuenes of ſinnes. <hi>As we forgeue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs.</hi> Iniuries doone vnto vs muſt be forgiuen &amp; forgoutte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Gen. chap. 50. ver. 21. Col. cap. 3. ver. 13</hi> If we be reuiled in worde, or euill intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:26314:6"/>indeed we muſt neither be hard to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue, nor haſtie to reuenge, wee muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue an hundred pence, if we wil be forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ten thoſand talents. <hi>Mat. cap. 18. ver. 35.</hi> Our forgiuing of other is not the cauſe why wee are pardoned. Gods mercy is the cauſe. <hi>Epheſi. cap. 2. ver. 45.</hi> but it is a certaine argument that God hath, and will forgeue vs, yf wee can finde in our hearts vnfeynedly to forgeue other. <hi>Mat. cap. 6. ver. 14.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5 And lead vs not into temptation, but deliuer vs from euil.</hi> That is to ſay, Deliuer vs from euill, that wee bee not carried into temptation. By temptation are meant all euill motions, which do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure vs to ſinne. By euyl, I vnderſtande the Deuilliſo that this is the meaning of this petition: though euyll motions (O Lord) do continually aſſault vs and fight againſt our ſoules, yet aſſiſt vs mightily with thy grace, that wee neuer be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. We deſire Gods defence againſt our enimie, &amp; we haue great need ſo to doe. The Diuell is mighty: <hi>Epheſi. cap. 6. ver. 12.</hi> Wee weake, and not able
<pb facs="tcp:26314:6"/>of our ſelues too withſtand him. <hi>Epheſi. 6. ver. 11. Coloſ. chap. 1. ver. 11.</hi> But in Chriſte we ouercome: for ſtronger is hee that is in vs, then he that is in the worlde. <hi>1. Iohn. cap. 4. ver. 4.</hi> If wee needed not Gods ayde, this prayer were in vaine. We are taught in this petition, that God leadeth ſome into temptation. <hi>Eſay. cap. 6 ver. 10 Rom. cap. 1. ver 24.</hi> The wordes are plaine. <hi>And leade vs not into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> It ſeemeth ſtrange that God ſhuld lead into temptation. It is ſtrange, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, to mans reaſon, but Gods doing is aboue our reaſon. His iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes iuſt, though they bee often ſecrete: and God then leadeth intoo temptation, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he puniſheth one ſinne by another: &amp; when by taking away his ſpirite, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection he leaueth man to himſelfe. <hi>For thine is the kingdome, and the power, and the glory for euer. Amen.</hi> We may bee bolde too aſke, and ſure to obtaine at Gods handes our godly deſires, for his kingdome, power, and glory cannot bee taken from him. Gods kingdome is mightie glorious &amp; euerlaſting. Earthly
<pb facs="tcp:26314:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26314:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26314:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26314:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26314:9"/>Princes if they bee compared with God are nothing, and theyr kingdomes laſte but a while. Wicked men had not neede to wage battell againſt the Lorde, they fight in vayne and hurt themſelues moſt. <hi>Dan. cap. 4. ver. 32. Gods kingdome</hi> wil be aloft, do what they can. <hi>Dan. cap. 4. ver 31. Ephe. cap. 1. ver. 21.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God geue vs grace to be &amp; to continue his children, that wee may haue a crowne of glory in his euerlaſting kingdome for his Chriſtes ſake. Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is any among you afflicted? let him pray. Iames, chap. 5. ver. 13.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26314:9"/>
                  <head>¶ Faith is the gift of God. <hi>Philip. Cap. 1. ver. 29.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Faith is an aſſured knowledge of Gods fatherly goodwill vnto vs by Ieſus Chriſte, and a truſt in the ſame good will, which hath ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with it an earneſt care to liue a godly life.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Articles of our <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Beleeue in God, &amp;c.</hi> To beleeue in God, is to put our whole truſt &amp; affiance in god. We muſt apply this belief euery man to himſelf, otherwyſe it will not profite vs. The plaiſter, if it be not layd to the wounde, will neuer heale the ſore. The iuſt man ſhal liue by his owne faith. <hi>Rom. cap. 1. ver. 17. The father almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26314:10"/>&amp;c. God is almighty, becauſe althings are vnder his gouernment, and are ruled not by chaunce, but by his heauenly proui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dence. <hi>Dan. cap 4, ver. 32. Mat. cap. 10. ver. 29.30. Ephe. cap. 1. ver. 11.</hi> If it were not thus, Sathan and the wicked, who can do nothing without Gods ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, <hi>Iob. cap. 1. ver. 2.</hi> would eaſily o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe vs. <hi>Maker of heauen and earth.</hi> By heauen and earth are meant al creatures whatſoeuer and whereſoeuer they be. <hi>Apoc. cap. 10. ver. 6.</hi> When wee confeſſe God to be maker of al creatures, wee doe not deny that he hath care of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing them in theyr eſtate. <hi>Heb. cap. 1. ver. 3.</hi> That were in deede the high way to ouerthrowe his prouidence: and ſuche thoughtes doe not become the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND in Ieſus Chriſte. &amp;c.</hi> The Sonne of GOD is called Ieſus, becauſe hee ſaueth his people from theyr ſinnes. <hi>Math. cap. 1. ver. 21.</hi> His name is according to his office. He is
<pb facs="tcp:26314:10"/>called Chriſte, becauſe hee was annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the giftes of the holy Ghoſte, not by meaſure as we are, <hi>Ephe. cap. 4. ver. 7.</hi> But without meaſure. <hi>Iohn. cap. 3. ver. 34.</hi> That he might powre on vs great ſtore of heauenly graces. Our pouertie is great, but by Ieſus Chriſte we are conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally enriched: his Storehouſe cannot be emptied and his Fountaine can neuer be dryed vp. The Sonne of GOD was annoynted a Prophet, to open vnto vs the will of God and the glad tidinges of the Goſpell. <hi>Luke cap. 4. ver. 18.</hi> He was moynted a Prieſt too redeeme vs from eternall deathe by the Sacrifice of his owne body, offered once, not often, by himſelfe, not by others. <hi>Heb. cap. 9. ver. 26.28.</hi> And to make continual inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for vs miſerable ſinners. <hi>Heb. cap 7. ver. 25.</hi> He was annoynted a king to gouerne vs by his worde, which is his Scepter, and by his Spirite, whiche is the earneſt of our inheritaunce. <hi>His onely Sonne our Lorde.</hi> Chriſt is our lorde, becauſe wee are not our owne
<pb facs="tcp:26314:11"/>but his. Wee are his, becauſe we are bought with a price. <hi>1. Cor. cap. 6. ver. 20.</hi> Not with ſiluer and golde, but with his precious blood, <hi>1. Pet. chap. 1. ver. 18.19.</hi> Wee haue good cauſe too loue Chriſte: For hee bought vs dearely. <hi>Act. cap. 20. ver. 28. Apocal. cap. 5. ver. 9.</hi> Wee muſt honour and feare him: For he is our Lorde. <hi>Malach. cap. 1. ver. 6. Which was conceaued by the Holy Ghoſte.</hi> If Chriſte had beene conceaued by man, he had not beene voyde of ſinne: <hi>Iohn chap. 3. ver. 6. Iob, cap. 25. ver. 5.6</hi> and therefore vnfit to deliuer vs from ſin. <hi>Heb cap. 7. ver. 26. Borne of the Virgin Mary.</hi> Chriſte was like vnto vs in all things, onely ſin except. <hi>Heb. cap. 4. ver. 15.</hi> He tooke our nature vpon him. <hi>Heb. cap. 2. ver. 14.</hi> It is happy for vs that hee did ſo: for by this meanes the Deuil that had power of death, is deſtroyed, and we are reconciled vnto the fauour of GOD. <hi>Heb. cap. 2. ver. 14.17 Suffered vnder Pontius Pilate.</hi> Chriſtes life vppon the earth did not much differ from death: but a little before and at his death, bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barbarous
<pb facs="tcp:26314:11"/>crueltie was practiſed. <hi>Math. chap. 27. ver. 26.28.29.30.38.39.40.42.43.</hi> he was innocent by the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Pilate, but moſt vniuſtly condemned by that wicked hypocrite. <hi>Math. cap. 27. ver. 24.</hi> Chriſt was free from ſin: <hi>1. Iohn cap. 3. ver. 5.</hi> and therfore ſuffered not for his, but for our ſinnes. <hi>Rom. chap. 4. ver. 25. 2. Cor. chap. 5. ver. 21.</hi> If any ſay, that notwithſtanding Chriſtes death, ſin doth ſtill remaine euen in the faithful: <hi>1. Iohn. 1. ver. 8.</hi> hee may bee anſwered, that ſinne doeth bite, but not deuoure them. The ſheelde of faith may be wounded, but it cannot be ſtricken through. <hi>Was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified.</hi> The death of the croſſe was moſt greeuous of al other deaths: it was accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Gods owne mouth. <hi>Deut. chap. 21 ver. 23.</hi> Chriſt did abide the death of the croſſe. <hi>Philip. cap. 2. ver. 8.</hi> He was made a curſe to redeeme vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the curſe of the lawe. <hi>Galat. chap. 2. ver. 13.</hi> ſo that wee may be now aſſured that Satans head is broken. <hi>Gen. chap. 3. ver. 15.</hi> and that the hande writing which was againſt vs, is put out by Ieſus Chriſte, and faſtened
<pb facs="tcp:26314:12"/>to his croſſe. <hi>Col. cap. 2. ver. 14.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dead.</hi> Gods iuſtice could not bee ſatiſfied for our ſinnes, but by the death of the Sonne of GOD. <hi>Heb. cap. 2. ver. 9.17.</hi> It was therfore neceſſary for vs that he ſhoulde dye the death. If any meruaile why we dye, when Chriſte hath dyed for vs, they may bee aunſwered that death is greeuous, but not deadly too Gods Children: that it dwelleth in them, but hath not dominion ouer them: and that they dye, but doe paſſe by the deathe of the body, as by a gate of eternall life. <hi>2. Cor. cap. 5. ver. 1.2. Philip. cap. 1. ver. 23.</hi> Seeing therfore that the loſſe of this ſhort and tranſitory life, is the high way and entraunce into Gods kingdome, wee muſt not be afraide to dye, when our lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God doth call vs, vnleſſe wee make greater account of earth then of heauen, and of the company of men then of God and his Angels.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And buried.</hi> Chriſte was buryed by an honorable Counſellour <hi>Ioſeph of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramathia,</hi> who begged his body of <hi>Pilat. Mark. chap. 15. verſ. 43.</hi> His burial is
<pb facs="tcp:26314:12"/>mencioned too aſſure vs that hee dyed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He deſcended into Hel</hi> (that is to ſay) He ſuffered the torments of Hel, and did abide the moſt bitter ſorowes of death, <hi>Acts. chap. 2. ver. 24.</hi> As if hee had beene forſaken of GOD his father. <hi>Matth. chap. 27. ver. 46.</hi> All this was for our cauſe. <hi>Eſay. chap. 63. ver. 4.5.</hi> When wee are in great torment, and griefe for our ſinnes, when we are euen at the brink of deſpayre, then it will bee a notable ſheelde to beare of all grieuous aſſaultes, too remember that our Sauiour Chriſte went downe into Hell, to deliuer vs from the torments thereof. This leſſon if it <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſurely learned and ſetled in our hartes, wyll heale a wounded conſcience, wyll tayſe vs vp from the gates of Hell, and wil in our greateſt diſtreſſe be very ſweet <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto vs. Chriſt did not diſcend into hell, to fetch from thence the godly Patriarkes, and other which died well before his com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ming in the fleſh: that is a wicked dreme, and hath neyther grounde to ſtand on, nor <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight to ſhewe it by in Gods Booke, for
<pb facs="tcp:26314:13"/>they were neuer there. <hi>Eccleſiaſt. chap. 12. ver. 7. 1. Cor. chap. 10. ver. 3.4. The thirde day he roſe againe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead.</hi> Chriſtes enimies did what they could to keepe him downe: they laide a ſtone vpon his graue, they ſealed the ſtone, they made the graue ſure with a watch: <hi>Mat. 27. ver 65.66.</hi> but al was in vaine, for Chriſt roſe the third day from death. <hi>Math. chap. 28. ver. 6.7.</hi> Chriſtes reſurrection was great loſſe vnto Satan, it ſwalowed vp death, and broke in peeces the bonds of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil: <hi>Coll. cap, 2. ver. 15.</hi> It is gainfull too vs, for therby we haue a ſure pledge of our reſurrection: <hi>1. Cor. cap. 15. ver. 20.21.22.</hi> and are made partakers of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of Chriſt. <hi>Rom. cap. 4. ver. 25. He aſcended into heauen.</hi> Chriſts aſcen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding into heauen is manifeſtly prooued in the Scriptures: <hi>Mark. cap. 16. ver. 19 Act. cap. 1. ver. 9. Heb. cap. ver. 14.</hi> Hee aſcended into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to prepare vs a place. <hi>Iohn. cap. 14. ver. 2.</hi> and to pray continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for vs vnto God his father. <hi>Rom. ca. 8. ver. 34.</hi> Seing that Chriſt is our Attur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney and pleadeth for vs, we may go bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:26314:13"/>vnto the throne of grace, that we may receiue mercy &amp; finde grace to helpe vs in time of neede. <hi>Heb. cap. ver. 16.</hi> If Chriſt be in heauen bodily, as we are plainely taught in Gods booke by S. <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; by S. <hi>Paul: Act. cap. 3. ver. 21. Phil. chap. 3. ver. 20. Heb. cap. 9. ver. 24.</hi> Then he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is nor can be bodily in many places at once. It is true that Chriſte promiſed his Apoſtles, &amp; in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other, that he would be with them vnto the ende of the worlde. <hi>Mat. cap. 28. ver. 20.</hi> But hee ment by the vertue of his ſpirite: <hi>Ioh. cap. 14. ver. 18.</hi> in which ſenſe S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſayth that Chriſt aſcended aboue all heauens too fulfill all things. <hi>Ephe. cap. 4. ver. 10. And ſitteth at the right hand of God the father al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie.</hi> God is a ſpirit: <hi>Ioh. cap. 4. ver. 24.</hi> He hath neither hands, eyes, armes, eares, nor ſuch like as ſome haue imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. I graunt the Scripture giueth eies, armes, eares, &amp;c, vnto God, not that hee hath ſuche, but to helpe our weakenes by ſuch maner of ſpeaches. Chriſt is ſayd to ſit at the right hand of God, becauſe he is aboue all rule and power, and might, and
<pb facs="tcp:26314:14"/>dominion and euery name that is named, not in this worlde onely, but alſo in the world to come. <hi>Ephe. chap. 1. ver. 21.22.</hi> Seeing that Ieſus Chriſte is of ſo great power, Gods children may aſſure them ſelues of a ſingular defence, and the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked maye reckon of a greeuous ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>From thence ſhal he come to iudge the quicke and the dead.</hi> Chriſt when hee was on the earth was moſt vniuſtly iudged: but in the great day he ſhall ſit in Iudgement, and all the worlde ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before his Maieſtie. <hi>2. Cor. cap. 5. ver. 10.</hi> none ſhall eſcape his iudgement. <hi>Apoc. chap. 20. ver. 12.13.</hi> Dead and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſhall come before his preſence. <hi>Acts. chap. 10. ver. 42. 2. Timoth. cap. 4. ver. 1.</hi> If any ſaye that death is the houſe of all fleſhe: <hi>Hebr. chap. 9. ver. 27.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that none ſhall bee aliue at Chriſtes ſecond and glorious appearance, he may be anſweared, that as they which eyther haue already dyed, or ſhall dye heereafter
<pb facs="tcp:26314:14"/>before the day of Iudgement, haue and ſhall put of the <hi>Subſtaunce</hi> of theyr bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, ſo they which ſhall bee aliue at that tyme ſhall put of, not the <hi>Subſtaunce</hi> of theyr bodyes as the other haue, but the <hi>Qualities</hi> of theyr bodyes: which is no doubt a kinde of death: and thus is the place of Saint Paule to be vnderſtoode <hi>Wee ſhall not all ſleepe, but we ſhall all be chaunged. 1. Corinth. Chapter. 15. verſe. 51.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This day of Iudgement will bee a comfortable and ioyfull day to God his children: <hi>Luke chap. 21. verſe. 28. Philip chap. 3. ver. 20.21. 1. Theſſa. chap. 4. ver. 16.17.</hi> for then they ſhal haue ful poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, aſwel in body as ſoule, of Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting kingdome. <hi>Matthew cap. 25. ver. 34.49.</hi> It will bee a fearefull day to the wicked. <hi>2. Theſſalonians chap. 1. verſe 7.8.9.</hi> For then Gods vengeaunce ſhall bee plentifully powred vppon them. <hi>Apocalips. chap. 20. ver. 15. Matthewe chap. 25. ver. 41.46.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26314:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>I beleeue in the holy Ghoſte.</hi> By ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt I vnderſtand the third perſon of the holy Trinitie, proceeding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the ſonne. <hi>Iohn cap. 15. ver. 26.</hi> who as he is true God: <hi>Act cap. 5. ver. 3.4. 1. Cor. cap. 3. ver. 16.</hi> ſo by his inwarde and heauenly working in our harts, he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureth vs that wee are of the number of Gods children, <hi>Rom. chap. 8. ver. 16.</hi> and that we are &amp; ſhalbe cloched with Chriſt, as with a precious garment, and haue Chriſtes benefices plentifully and with a full horne powred vpon vs. <hi>The holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church,</hi> that is to ſay, I beleeue that almightie God had from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the worlde, hath preſently in the world, and ſhall haue vntil the ende of the world his church on the earth. <hi>Ezdr. cap. 9. ver. 8. Eſay. cap. 29. ver. 18.22.</hi> though not alike viſible at al times in the eyes of men. <hi>Eſay. chap. 49. ver. 21, Dan. cap. 7. ver. 21.22. Apoc. chap. 12. ver. 6.</hi> The viſible Churche is the company of thoſe which make profeſſion too ſerue the true god in Chriſt The Church is called holy,
<pb facs="tcp:26314:15"/>not becauſe it is without ſinne, or cannot be duſked with ſome ſpot, (for the whole Church prayeth for pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their ſinnes) <hi>Math. cap. 6. ver. 12.</hi> But for that Ieſus Chriſte, who is the head of the Church, is holy and that the holineſſe of the Church is begun in this life. The Church is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Catholike</hi> or vniuerſall, becauſe it is not tyed to any time, perſons, or place. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zech cap. 11. ver. 22.23. Mat. cap. 23. ver 37.38.39. Act. cap. 13. ver. 27.28.</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſcattered ouer the face of the world, according to the pleſure of almigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie God. This Catholike Church of God ſtandeth not in multitude of perſons, <hi>Act cap. 19. ver. 27. Apo. cap. 28. ver. 28.</hi> but in weight of trueth. <hi>Ephe. chap. 2. ver. 20</hi> otherwiſe Chriſte himſelfe and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles had not byn <hi>Catholike,</hi> for his flock was very litle. <hi>Luk. ca. 12. ver, 33.</hi> and the catholik or vniuerſal conſent of the world ſtoode againſt it. <hi>Acts. cap. 4. ver. 26.27. The communion of Saints.</hi> By <hi>Saints</hi> are mental the faithful wherſoeuer, ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by the holy Ghoſt: ſo that this is the meaning of this Article: I beleeue that
<pb facs="tcp:26314:16"/>there is a communion or felowſhip of and amongeſt the children of God. This com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munion or felowſhip of Saints is firſt, &amp; eſpecially with Ieſus Chriſt, who as he is the onely head of the Church: <hi>Col. cap. 1. ver. 18. Eph. cap. 4. ver. 15.16.</hi> So he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth life and ſpirituall giftes to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, who are his members. This commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion or felowſhip is alſo amongſt the god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly themſelues, &amp; appeareth euidently by vnitie of faith, by partaking of the holy Sacraments, &amp; laſtly by relieuing one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, either with ſpiritual graces, <hi>Heb cap. 3. ver. 13.1. Theſ. chap. 5. ver. 11.14.</hi> Which muſt bee vſed to the comfort and good of others according to our calling, or els w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> part of thoſe external bleſſings which the Lorde in mercy hath made vs ſtewards of. <hi>2. Cor. cap. 8. ver. 3.11.12. Heb. cap. 13. ver. 16. The forgeuenes of ſinnes: (that is to ſay)</hi> I beleeue that Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God hath, doth, and will forgiue me and al his children, al our ſinnes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted both before and after baptiſme, <hi>1. Iohn. cap. 1. ver. 7.1. Pet. cap. 2. verſ. 24.</hi> howe greate and many ſo euer they bee.
<pb facs="tcp:26314:16"/>
                  <hi>Eſay. cap. 1. ver. 18. Mat. cap. 12. ver. 31</hi> not for any worke or merite of ours, <hi>Luke cap. 17. ver. 10. Eſay cap. 43. ver. 25. and chap. 64. ver. 6.</hi> but for the death &amp; blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of the immaculat lambe Ieſus chriſt <hi>1. Pet. chap. 1. ver. 18.19. Apoc. chap. 1. ver. 5.</hi> With whoſe righteouſnes becauſe we are clothed, we may aſſure our ſelues that we are deliuered from eternal death, which is the ſtipende and wages of ſinne, <hi>Rom. cap. 6. ver. 23.</hi> Almightie god hath and doth beſtow many good things day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon vs, for which wee are greatly and deepely bound vnto his maieſtie: but this benefite of waſhing vs from our ſinnes in Chriſts blood, if it be compared with the other, doth as farre paſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond doeth the Peeble ſtone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The reſurrection of the body: (that is too ſay)</hi> I beleeue that all mens bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, euen the ſelfe ſame wee carrye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout vs in our life time, and no other then they, as touching the ſubſtaunce, (whether they rotte in the Graue, or bee any otherwiſe conſumed) ſhall bee
<pb facs="tcp:26314:17"/>rayſed vp againe at the laſt day, and bee ioyned to their ſoules. <hi>Iob. chap. 19. ver. 26.27.1. Cor. cap 1.5. ver. 52.53. Philip cap. 3. ver. 22.</hi> At which time the godly ſhal haue ful poſſeſſion of eternal life, and the wicked of eternall death. <hi>Iohn. cap. 5. ver. 28.29. The life euerlaſting,</hi> That is, to ſay: I beleeue, that as I haue the ſeede of eternal life already ſowne in my heart, which is very ſweete, and a ſure ſtaffe to reſt on in all miſeries of this life whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer: ſo I ſhall be perfectly happy in the life to come, and ſhal then &amp; there praiſe the Lorde God without ceaſſing, and yet without weatineſſe. <hi>Apoc. cap. 21. ver. 4.</hi> If Gods children do beleeue eternal life, then they neither can, nor ought to doubte of the certayntie of their ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for faith and doubting cannot ſtand togeather. <hi>2. Cor. chap. 13. ver. 5. Rom. chap. 8. verſ. 14.16.7.</hi> The Lorde for his mercy ſake increaſe our faith, and giue vs grace to liue alwayes in his feare, that when we ſhal leaue this tranſitorie life, we may haue the ende of our faith, which is the
<pb facs="tcp:26314:17"/>ſaluation of our ſoules purchaſed vnto vs by the precious death and bloodſhed of our Lorde and onely Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
               <p>Amen.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Without faith it is impoſsible to pleaſe GOD.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Heb. chap.</hi> 11. <hi>verſ.</hi> 6.</bibl>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:26314:18"/>
               <head>Sinne is a breaking of Gods <hi>law. 1. Iohn. 3. ver. 4. either in</hi> woorde, thought, or deed.</head>
               <head type="sub">The ten Commaundements of almgh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God. The firſt 4. Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments teache vs our duetie to God. The 6. laſt, teache vs our dutie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1 <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou ſhalt haue no other gods but me. that is,</hi> thou ſhalt put thy truſt in god only, &amp; worſhip him only. <hi>Deut. cap. 6. ver. 13. Mat. cap. 4. ver. 10.</hi> The Lord cannot abide to haue any ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with him. <hi>Deu. cap. 6. ver. 14.15.</hi> He will either haue al or none. <hi>Ezec. cap. 20. ver. 39. Ioſua cap. 24. ver. 23.24.</hi> They which truſt in any other then God alone, doe forget the Lorde. <hi>Pſalm. 44. ver: 20.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2 Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen Image, nor the likeneſſe of
<pb facs="tcp:26314:18"/>any thing that is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue, or in the earth beneath, or in the waters vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the earth: (that is)</hi> Thou ſhalt not make any Image, either to repreſent god who cannot be ſeene: <hi>Deu. cap. 4. ver. 12.15. Acts. cap. 17. ver. 29.</hi> Or to worſhip God by: <hi>Rom. cap. 1. ver. 23.25.</hi> for it is againſt this commandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bowe downe to them, nor worſhip the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (that is)</hi> thou ſhalt not ſhew ſo muche as outwarde reuerence vnto them, no not the bowing of the body, or any part ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: <hi>Exo. cap. 34, ver. 14. 2. Co. cap. 7. ver. 1. Rom. cap. 11. ver. 4.</hi> For Images are lying ſcholemaiſters. <hi>Ier. cap. 10. ver. 8.14.15. Abac. cap. 2. ver. 18.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3 Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine (that is)</hi> thou ſhalt neither ſweare often and vainly: <hi>Mat chap. 5. ver. 34.37. Iam. chap. 5. ver. 12.</hi> Much leſſe blaſphemouſly in thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon talke: <hi>Leuit. cap. 34. ver. 15.16.</hi> Neither forſweare thy ſelfe: <hi>Math. cap. 5. ver. 33.</hi> Neither conſent vnto them, which offend in this or any other wicked ſort. <hi>Eph. cap. 5. ver. 11.12.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26314:19"/>
               <p>But bicauſe the name of God is holy <hi>Pſa. 103. ver. 1.</hi> Thou ſhalt not defile it, but vſe it with great reuerence. <hi>Leuit. chap. 19. ver. 12.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is it lawfull to ſweare at al? it is, for the teſtifiyng of a truthe, whereby eyther Gods glory is promoted: <hi>1. Reg. cap. 22. ver. 14.</hi> or controuerſies ended amongeſt our neighbors. <hi>Gen. cap. 31. ver. 53. Heb cap. 6. ver. 16.</hi> Is it lawful too ſweare by Saints, or any other creature? No, wee muſt ſweare by God alone. <hi>Deut. cap. 6. ver. 13. Eſay. cap. 45. ver. 23.</hi> And that in the caſes before remembred: for a lawfull othe is a part of Gods worſhip. <hi>Eſay. cap. 19 ver. 18. Ierem. cap. 12. ver. 16.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4 Remember that thou keepe holy the Sabboth day: (that is)</hi> thou ſhalt ſpend that day in hearing gods moſt holy worde, in common prayers and ſuch like, to Gods glory and thine owne comforte. Is it not lawfull to haue ſome other ſette dayes for common and Chriſtian aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies? yes, no doubt, if ſuperſtition (that is to ſay) the eſteeming of one day more holy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another be abſent, &amp; the Lord god
<pb facs="tcp:26314:19"/>ſincerely honoured. But the Lordes day which we call the Sunday, is eſpecially appointed, becauſe of our weakeneſſe by Gods church in ſteed of the Iewes Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both. <hi>Actes. chap. 20. ver. 7. 1. Cor. cap. 16. ver. 2.</hi> They which abſent themſelues from Chriſtian meetings, where God is truely ſerued, either wilfully as Gods eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies do, or for diſpatch of buſines (which may be wel deferred) as worldlings doe, are guiltie, the one ſort of conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning God and his Church, both which are highly to be eſteemed. <hi>Mat. cap. 18. ver. 20. 1. Tim. chap. 3. ver. 15. Ephe. chap. 5. ver. 27.</hi> the other of preferring their greedie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, before the Lords vnſpeakeable mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. <hi>Mat. cap. 22. ver. 2.3.5.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſecond Table.</head>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5 HOnor thy Father and thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: (that is)</hi> giue reuerence to thy father and mother. <hi>Leuit. chap. 19. ver. 3. Gen. cap. 46. ver. 29. Col. chap. 3. ver. 20.</hi> and help them: if, and wherein they haue neede, as thou art able. <hi>Gen
<pb facs="tcp:26314:20"/>chap. 45. ver. 9.10.11. 1. Sam. chap. 22. ver. 3.4.</hi> And be alwayes humble and obe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dient vnto them in the Lord. <hi>Ephe. cap. 6 ver. 1.</hi> but neuer againſt the Lorde, <hi>Luke chap. 14. ver. 26.</hi> Muſt wee honour none but our Fathers and Mothers? Yes, al thoſe muſt be honoured, whom God hath any waies ſet ouer vs: as the Magiſtrate, <hi>Rom. cap. 13. ver. 1. Tit. cap. 3. ver. 1. 1. Pet. cap. 2. ver. 13.14.</hi> The Miniſter of Gods word, <hi>Heb. ca. 13. ver. 17. 1. Theſſ. cap. 5. ver. 12.13. 1. Tim. cap. 5. ver. 17.</hi> our bodily maiſters: <hi>1. Tim. cap. 6. ver. 1. Ephe. cap. 6 ver. 5.</hi> and ſuch like: But yet euer in, and neuer againſt the Lord.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6 Thou ſhalt not kill: (that is)</hi> thou ſhalt neither vſe any violence thy ſelf, nor be authour, or conſenting that any be vſed by other againſt thy neighbour. <hi>Leui. cap 19. ver. 16.</hi> Thou ſhalt neither be are ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred or malice againſt him. <hi>Math. cap. 5. verſe. 22. 1. Iohn. chap. 3. verſe. 15.</hi> Thou ſhalt neither ſecretly nor openly take away his good name. <hi>Pſalm. 101. ver. 5. Iam. chap. 4. ver. 11.</hi> Thou ſhalt vſe thy neighbour louingly both in woord
<pb facs="tcp:26314:20"/>and deed, <hi>1. Ioh. cap. 3. ver. 18.</hi> And thou muſte doe good euen vnto thy enimie. <hi>Exod. cap. 23. ver. 4.5. Math. cap. 5. ver. 44. Rom. chap. 12. ver. 20.</hi> Is it not lawful to put notable offenders to death? it is: not for priuate men, whoſe handes the Lord hath bound: <hi>Gen. chap. 9. ver. 6. Matth. cap. 26. ver. 52.</hi> But for the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, whom God hath armed with the ſword. <hi>Prou. cap. 20. ver. 26. Pſal. 101 ver. 8 Rom. chap. 13. ver. 4.</hi> If the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate condeme vs vniuſtly, muſt we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey? we muſt euen to the abiding of death. <hi>1. Pet. cap. 2. ver. 23.</hi> But yet commit our cauſe to God, who iudgeth iuſtly. <hi>2. Chronic. chap. 24. ver. 22. 1. Pet. chap. 2. ver. 23. Rom. cap. 12. ver. 19.</hi> And thinke our ſelues happy that we ſuffer for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſake. <hi>Mat. cap. 5. ver. 10. &amp; 16. ver 25. 1. Pet. cap. 2. ver. 19.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7 Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie, (that is)</hi> thou ſhalt keepe thy minde free from luſting after ſtrange fleſh. <hi>Mathew. chap. 5. ver. 28. 1. Cor. chap. 6. ver. 20</hi> And thy body and euery part thereof, free from all wantonneſſe: whether it be the
<pb facs="tcp:26314:21"/>committing of any whooriſhe and filthie deede: <hi>1. Cor. cap. 6. ver. 18.19.20. Heb. cap. 13. ver. 4.</hi> or corrupt talk: <hi>1. Cor. cap. 15. ver 33. Ephe. cap. 4, ver. 29.</hi> Or light behauiour. <hi>Iob. ca. 31. ver. 1.</hi> They which haue not the gift of continencie may and ought to marry: <hi>1. Cor. chap. 7. ver. 2.9. Heb cap. 13. ver. 4.</hi> But they muſt ioyne with ſuch as feare God. <hi>Gen. cap. 24. ver. 3.2. Cor. cap. 6. ver. 14.15.</hi> And with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of their parents. <hi>Gen. cap. 34. ver 4.1. Cor. cap. 7. ver. 37.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8 Thou ſhalt not ſteale (that is)</hi> thou ſhalt be ſo far of from committing theft, which the Princes lawes do puniſh with deeth, that thou ſhalt neither by vſurie, <hi>Ezech. cap. 18. ver. 8.13. Pſal. 15. ver. 5.</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of law, <hi>1. Cor. cap. 6. ver. 9.10.</hi> by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſures of commons, whereby the poore either are, or ought to be relieued. <hi>Mich. chap. 2. ver. 1.2.3. Deut. chap. 5. ver. 21.</hi> or by any meanes whatſoeuer defraude or oppreſſe any man in any matter. <hi>1. Theſ. 5. ver. 6.</hi> If thou haue ſinned in any of theſe ſorts (thou muſt make reſtitution: <hi>Nehe. ca. 5. ver. 11.12.13. Eze. ca. 33. ver. 15.</hi> &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:26314:21"/>ſteale no more, but labour rather with thy hands in the thing which is good, that thou maiſt haue to giue to him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> needeth. <hi>Eph. chap. 4 ver. 28.</hi> If falſe dealing muſt not be vſed in things that appertaine to this life: <hi>Leuit. chap. 19. ver. 11.</hi> much leſſe are Gods people, to bee ſpoyled of the foode of their ſoules, either by corrupting the word of life, or making marchaundiſe thereof <hi>2. Cor. chap. 2. ver. 17. and. chap. 4. ver 2.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9 Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witnes. againſt thy neighbour:</hi> (that is) thou ſhalt not put thy hand with the wicked, to be a falſe witneſſe, <hi>Exod. chap. 22. ver. 1</hi> either by word or othe: thou ſhalt not by re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiuing or reporting a lye, <hi>Exod. cap. 23. ver. 1.</hi> either impaire thy neighbours good name. <hi>Pſal. 15. ver. 3. Prou. cap. 22. ver. 1.</hi> or diminiſhe the leaſte parte of his goods, much leſſe endanger his life: Thou halt not miſconſtrue his woordes as the wicked doe. <hi>Matth. chap. 16. ver. 6. Act. chap. 6. ver. 13.14.</hi> But thou ſhalt caſt of lying, and ſpeake trueth vnto thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, <hi>Ephe. chap. 4. ver, 25.</hi> plainely, but yet louingly rebuking him, and not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:26314:22"/>him to ſinne. <hi>Leuit. chap. 19. ver. 17. Mat. cap. 18. ver. 15.</hi> As it is great wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe to beare falſe witneſſe any way, or to any end: ſo is it very lawfull to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe a trueth, either for the increaſe of Gods glory, the ending of controuerſies amongſt our neighbours, or for the ſafety of our Prince &amp; Country. To refuſe too witneſſe or vtter the truthe in theſe caſes, either by worde or othe, is too be wicked and falſe witneſſes.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10 Thou ſhalt not couet thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours houſe. Thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbours wife, nor his ſeruant, nor his maid, nor his Oxe, nor his Aſſe, nor any thing that is his.</hi> (that is) thou ſhalt be ſo far from doing the leaſt wrong vnto thy neighbour, in any of thy outwarde do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, that thou ſhalt not once think or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to hurt him any way. <hi>Zac. cap. 8. ver. 17.</hi> Gods lawe doeth not onely binde our bodies, &amp; euery part therof to obedience, but our mindes alſo: it is therefore ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual. <hi>Rom. cap. ver. 14.</hi> Gods lawe doeth forbid all vnlawfull concupiſcence: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vnlawfull concupiſcence, though it
<pb facs="tcp:26314:22"/>burſt not out into outward act, is ſinne, <hi>Rom. cap. 7. ver. 7.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>CAn any of Gods children keepe gods commaundementes perfectly in this life? no, not one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, onely Ieſus Chriſt excepted, who was free from ſin. <hi>2. Cor. chap. 5. ver. 21. 1. Pet: cap. 2. ver. 22.</hi> not one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſay eyther was, is, or ſhalbe able to keepe Gods commaundements in this life.</p>
                  <p>SEeing that none can keepe gods com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in this life: why wil the Lorde haue them ſo exactly and ſeuerely preached? I anſwere, that we ſeeing in the law as in a glaſſe, what greeuous ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners we are, and how by our corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture we doe incline, yea rather are carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed headlong to ſin, <hi>Rom. cap. 3. ver. 20. &amp;. cap. 7. ver. 8.</hi> might haue feeling of, &amp; be ſory for our ſinnes, and ſo be led by the law, as by a ſcholemaiſter to Ieſus chriſt: that we might be made righteous by faith in him. <hi>Galat. chap. 3. ver. 24.</hi> by whoſe ſtripes we are healed. <hi>1. Pet. ca. 2. ver. 24.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26314:23"/>
                  <p>The Lord poſſeſſe our hearts with his holy ſpirite, that wee may be carefull too pleaſe, and affraid to diſpleaſe him. The Lorde forgiue vs all our ſinnes, euen for his great mercies ſake. Amen.</p>
                  <p>OH that my wayes were directed to keepe thy ſtatutes. <hi>Pſal. 119. ver. 5.</hi> Open mine eies that I may ſee the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of thy Lawe. <hi>ver. 18.</hi> I am a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger vpon earth: hide not thy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from mee. <hi>verſ. 19.</hi> Make mee to vnderſtande the way of thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes, and I will meditate in the wonderful workes. <hi>verſe. 27.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
